Guide to the Joel Garreau Papers, 1954-1994
George Mason University Libraries
- Series 1: Edge City, 1959-February 1994
  - Subseries 1.5: Race/Poverty, July 1982-August 1992
    - Afro Texan History-Houston, October 1991-August 1992 (Box 35, Folder 18)
      Articles, newsletters and other documents about the history of Houston, Texas.
    - Theory Racism, May 1991 (Box 35, Folder 19)
      Two copies of an article about race.
    - Blacks-A Race Divided (Baraka, Steele), February 1991 (Box 35, Folder 20)
      An article on the state of Africans Americans after the civil rights movement.
    - Values KKK, February 1990 (Box 35, Folder 21)
      An article about the decline of the Ku Klux Klan.
    - Black Enterprise, June 1991 (Box 35, Folder 22)
      The June 1991 issue of Black Enterprise magazine.
    - Traditional Black Colleges and Universities, 1990 (Box 35, Folder 23)
      "The Historical and Contemporary Structure of Traditional Black Colleges and Universities".
    - Black Population Geography, 1990 (Box 35, Folder 24)
      "A Statistical and Geographical Portrait of the Black Population".
    - Prices vs. American Dream, July 1988 (Box 35, Folder 25)
      An article and a booklet about Race and Housing. Theory
    - Housing-Class Conflict, February 1989 (Box 35, Folder 26)
      An article about housing grants and subsidized housing. Problems/Solutions
  - Subseries 1.6: Transportation, 1981-April 1992
    Documents from Joel Garreau's book "Edge City" dealing with transportation and congestion. With the growth of edge cities, the need for improved and enlarged infrastructure grew as well.
    - Sources Transportation, June 1990 (Box 36, Folder 1)
      A press release about linking transportation and economic development.
    - Transportation Suburban Gridlock, March 1987-July 1990 (Box 36, Folder 2)
      Articles, agendas, newsletters, documents, designs, contact information, correspondence, proposals and maps about development in Fairfax, Virginia. Also included is "From Country Crossroads to Suburban City: The Transformation of Tysons Corner, Virginia" by Shelley Mastran. Problems/Solutions
    - Transportation Board of Trade Washington, D.C., Undated (Box 36, Folder 3)
      A pamphlet for a seminar "Transportation Management for Employers, Employees and a Better Community".
    - Traffic Stress, April 1986-January 1989 (Box 36, Folder 4)
      Articles about development and the stress of traffic.
    - Urban Mass Transit Administration, Undated (Box 36, Folder 5)
      Samual L. Zimmerman's Department of Transportation business card.
    - Automobile, November 1987-November 1990 (Box 36, Folder 6)
      Documents, press releases, magazines, correspondence, advertisements and articles about the changing role of automobiles. Theory
    - Automobiles Transportation Management, December 1986-September 1990 (Box 36, Folder 7)
      Articles, "Issues in Transportation and Growth Management", contact information, "A Toolbox for Alleviating Traffic Congestion" and correspondence about traffic congestion management. Theory
    - Galleria, March 1990 (Box 36, Folder 8)
      "Comprehensive Transportation Strategy" for the Houston area, around the Galleria mall.
    - Travel Trends, February 1985 (Box 36, Folder 9)
      "Demographic Change and Recent Worktrip Travel Trends".
    - Montgomery County Traffic, December 1989 (Box 36, Folder 10)
      An article about traffic congestion in Montgomery County, Maryland.
    - Transportation Dave Cole, Undated (Box 36, Folder 11)
      Notes and transcripts of interviews with David Cole and John Wright. Problems/Solutions
    - Traffic Northern Virginia, July 1988-September 1990 (Box 37, Folder 1)
      Articles and magazines about traffic problems in suburban areas. Problems/Solutions
    - Transportation General, December 1990 (Box 37, Folder 2)
      The Winter 1990 issue of The Region magazine from the Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments.
    - Transportation Alcohol Fuel, July 1989 (Box 37, Folder 3)
      An article about ethanol. Problems/Solutions
    - Transportation Future of Automobiles, May-August 1989 (Box 37, Folder 4)
      Articles about the development of smarter cars. Problems/Solutions
    - Transportation "Outlook for the 90s", July 1990 (Box 37, Folder 5)
      The Summer 1990 issue of The Region magazine from the Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments. Problems/Solutions
    - "Commuting in America", 1987 (Box 37, Folder 6)
      "Commuting in America: A National Report on Commuting Patterns and Trends. Problems/Solutions
    - Transportation Commuting, 1981-October 1990 (Box 37, Folder 7)
      Articles, transcripts of articles, graphs, charts, lists of policies, contact lists, press releases and information tables about the psychology of being in traffic. Problems/Solutions
    - Transportation Traffic Congestion, February 1991 (Box 37, Folder 8)
      "Stuck in Traffic: Coping with Peak-Hour Traffic Congestion" by Anthony Downs.
    - Transportation Fast Train, June 1989 (Box 37, Folder 9)
      An article about proposed high speed train routes. Problems/Solutions
    - Transportation Trains, December 1991-April 1992 (Box 37, Folder 10)
      Articles about high speed trains in America as well as correspondence and critical response about "Supertrains" by Joseph Vranich. Problems/Solutions
    - Transportation Fuel, Undated (Box 37, Folder 11)
      An article and graphs about fuel. Problems/Solutions
    - Transportation Myths and Facts About Transportation and Growth, Undated (Box 37, Folder 12)
      "Myths and Facts about Transportation and Growth" from the Urban land Institute and a business card. Problems/Solutions
    - Transportation Commuter Traffic, October 1985-July 1988 (Box 37, Folder 13)
      Articles and publications about commuting in the New York City, Washington, D.C. and Miami areas. Problems/Solutions
    - Transportation Railway Trains, September 1990 (Box 37, Folder 14)
      Articles about the development of railways. Problems/Solutions
    - Transportation Traffic Management, December 1986 (Box 37, Folder 15)
      "Transportation Management Associations: Battling Suburban Traffic Congestion" by C. Kenneth Orski. Problems/Solutions
    - Transportation National, November 1990 (Box 37, Folder 16)
      "Coming and Going", "Mobility With Pepperoni and Extra Cheese: A Parable" by Alan E. Pisarski and "Travel Demand in the 1990s"by Alan E. Pisarski. Problems/Solutions
    - Transportation London Roads, April 1990 (Box 37, Folder 17)
      An article about transportation problems in London. Problems/Solutions
    - Transportation Metrorail, February-October 1988 (Box 37, Folder 18)
      Correspondence, press release and an essay about the Washington, D.C. area Metro. Problems/Solutions
    - Transportation California, March 1991 (Box 37, Folder 19)
      "Transportation Efficiency Tackling Southern California's Air Pollution and Congestion" by Michael Cameron. Problems/Solutions
    - Transportation Townless Highways for the Motorist, Undated (Box 37, Folder 20)
      "Townless Highways for the Motorist: A Proposal for the Automobile Age" by Benton Mackaye and Lewis Mumford. Problems/Solutions
    - Transportation D.C. Region, December 1984-May 1990 (Box 38, Folder 1)
      Articles, correspondence, illustrations, fliers, notes and documents about transportation in the Washington, D.C. area. Problems/Solutions
    - Transportation Outer Beltway Notes, May 1986-October 1988 (Box 38, Folder 2)
      Notes and a study on the Washington, D.C. Western Bypass. Problems/Solutions
    - Transportation Public, January 1988 (Box 38, Folder 3)
      An article and an essay about the future of public transportation. Problems/Solutions
    - Transportation Satellite Airport, July 1990 (Box 38, Folder 4)
      An article about airports in the vicinity of major cities. Problems/Solutions
    - Transportation Public Private Partnerships, April-July 1989 (Box 38, Folder 5)
      Articles, press releases, a list of reports and policy lists for Opportunities for Participation in public transportation. Also included is the U.S. Department of Transportation Urban Mass Transportation Administration's "Suburban Mobility Parking Initiative Year 2". Problems/Solutions
    - Transportation Parking, October 1983-May 1990 (Box 38, Folder 6)
      Articles, rough drafts of essays, memos, maps, seminar descriptions, a list of conference speakers and correspondence about transportation and parking. Also included is a profile of E.M. Risse and "Report of the Citizens Committee for the Review of Land Use and Transportation Planning for Fairfax County". Problems/Solutions
    - Transportation Suburban Gridlock, January-September 1989 (Box 38, Folder 7)
      Articles and press releases about highway gridlock. Problems/Solutions
    - Transportation Toll Roads (Private), June 1989 (Box 38, Folder 8)
      An article about highway improvement. Problems/Solutions
    - Virginia Commuter Rail, November 1988 (Box 38, Folder 9)
      An article about the Virginia Commuter Rail program.
    - Transportation Virginia's Problems, January 1987-November 1988 (Box 38, Folder 10)
      Correspondence and articles about Virginia highways.
    - Transportation Northern Virginia Network, July-October 1988 (Box 38, Folder 11)
      Correspondence and essays on mobility in Northern Virginia. Problems/Solutions
    - Transportation Washington Bypass, November 1988 (Box 38, Folder 12)
      Articles and maps about a proposed new highway near Washington, D.C. Problems/Solutions
    - Florida Demographics and Journey to Work, Undated (Box 39, Folder 1)
      Data tables, correspondence and "Florida Demographics and Journey to Work" from the Center for Urban Transportation Research.
    - Transportation Projects, February 1987-July 1989 (Box 39, Folder 2)
      Articles, newsletters and reports of various transportation projects.
    - Urban Transportation Baerwald, November 1983-November 1984 (Box 39, Folder 3)
      Articles about transportation by Thomas J. Baerwald. Theory
    - Urban Land Institute, Undated (Box 39, Folder 4)
      "12 Tools for Improving Mobility and Managing Congestion" from the Urban Land Institute. Theory
    - Local Beltway Travel Time Study, April 1988 (Box 39, Folder 5)
      "1987 Beltway Travel Time Study" from the Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments. Numbers
    - 1987 Washington-Baltimore Regional Air Passenger Survey, May 1989 (Box 39, Folder 6)
      "1987 Washington-Baltimore Regional Air Passenger Survey Volume II: Geographic Findings" from the Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments. Numbers
    - Local Car and Passenger Counts, November 1987 (Box 39, Folder 7)
      "1987 Metro Core Cordon Count of Vehicular and Passenger Volumes" from the Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments. Numbers
    - D.C. Area Local Commuting, May 1988-June 1990 (Box 39, Folder 8)
      Maps, graphs, "Arterial Travel Time Survey" and "Baltimore-Washington Bi-Regional Travel Patterns". Numbers
    - Intermodal Surface Transportation Efficiency Act of 1991, November 1991 (Box 39, Folder 9)
      The Conference Report for the Intermodal Surface Transportation Efficiency Act of 1991. Problems/Solutions
    - Super Commuters, December 1989 (Box 39, Folder 10)
      An article about people who commute over 50 miles a day each way. Numbers
    - Local Transportation and Growth, June 1991 (Box 39, Folder 11)
      Bruce Adams' business card and "A Legacy of Excellence for the Washington Region" from the Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments. Numbers
  - Subseries 1.7: Numbers, January 1981-April 1992
    Documents from Garreau's files containing numbers and statistics and the results of various studies. Many of the reports focus on office space markets and real estate.
    - Claritas Stats, October-December 1989 (Box 39, Folder 12)
      Maps, floor layouts, population statistics and demographic information for a part of the Atlanta area.
    - Joel Garreau Project MSA Tracts, October 1989 (Box 39, Folder 13 (Oversize Box 65))
      Population statistics in Los Angeles, Chicago, Oakland, Detroit and Miami. OVERSIZE BOX 65
    - National Blacks, August 1989 (Box 39, Folder 14)
      An article about racism and poverty.
    - Print Outs by Joel Garreau, February 1987 (Box 40, Folder 1)
      print outs of articles and tables showing office space square footage.
    - Early Drafts Cities, February 1987-January 1988 (Box 40, Folder 2)
      Articles, correspondence and proposals for Garreau's "Edge City".
    - National Women Employed, October 1986 (Box 40, Folder 3)
      A publication about female employment.
    - National Population, September 1988-June 1989 (Box 40, Folder 4)
      Articles, cities ranked by population and population estimates.
    - National Population Growth, Undated (Box 40, Folder 5)
      "Selfward Bound? Personal Preference Patterns and the Changing Map of American Society" by Wilbur Zelinsky.
    - National Reapportionment, January 1988 (Box 40, Folder 6)
      Articles and lists of proposed changes about a redistribution of seats in Congress.
    - National Retail, Undated (Box 40, Folder 7)
      A document providing the ratio of new square feet of shopping center to births in the U.S.
    - Trends in Socio-Economics, Undated (Box 40, Folder 8)
      "Trends in Socio-Economics Characteristics Related to Transit Usage" for Washington, D.C.
    - Suburban America, September 1991 (Box 40, Folder 9)
      "The Suburbs Rule" by William Schneider.
    - Suburban Revolution, March 1991 (Box 40, Folder 10)
      "The Suburban Revolution" by Ted Kenney.
    - Technology West Virginia, November 1991 (Box 40, Folder 11)
      Articles and correspondence about jobs in West Virginia.
    - National Top Growth Counties, September 1991 (Box 40, Folder 12)
      An article about fast growing counties.
    - "A New Area In Road Policy", June 1990-September 1991 (Box 40, Folder 13)
      "A New Era In Road Policy" by James T. Drummond and "The Privatization of Metropolitan America" by Bruce D. McDowell.
    - Comstock Investment Strategy Review, July 1988 (Box 40, Folder 14)
      Articles with tables about housing prices.
    - National Office Space, September 1988-January 1991 (Box 40, Folder 15)
      Articles and information tables about office space.
    - Phoenix Office Market Survey, 1990 (Box 40, Folder 16)
      "Metropolitan Phoenix Office Market Survey 3rd Quarter 1990".
    - National Office Space Construction, October 1988-February 1991 (Box 40, Folder 17)
      An article about and lists of cities based on office market size.
    - Personal Gas Consumption, 1984 (Box 40, Folder 18)
      "Personal Gasoline Consumption, Population Patterns, and Metropolitan Structure: The United States, 1960-1970" by Wilbur Zelinsky and David F. Sly.
    - National Office Operating Costs, Undated (Box 40, Folder 19)
      An article about the price of office space in Washington, D.C.
    - National Home Prices, March 1989-June 1990 (Box 40, Folder 20)
      Two reports on home and real estate prices.
    - House Prices Philly, December 1988-January 1989 (Box 40, Folder 21)
      An article about housing prices in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.
    - National Housing Prices, February-December 1989 (Box 40, Folder 22)
      Articles about housing prices.
    - National Industrial Property, Undated (Box 40, Folder 23)
      Brochures, contact information and magazines for commercial real estate.
    - National Land Prices In Japan, March 1990 (Box 40, Folder 24)
      An article about rising land prices in Japan.
    - Census Bureau Males White, September 1991 (Box 40, Folder 25)
      An article about white males in small businesses.
    - Metro Marketplace, October 1991 (Box 40, Folder 26)
      A newsletter from the Washington Post Metro Marketplace.
    - National Malls, January 1991 (Box 40, Folder 27)
      A list of the top 50 mall owners.
    - National International Office Market Report, December 1988 (Box 40, Folder 28)
      The 1989 International Office Market Report.
    - National Transit, October 1991 (Box 41, Folder 1)
      Articles about transit policy and transportation issues.
    - Office Space U.S., December 1987 (Box 41, Folder 2)
      Listings of office buildings.
    - National Job Skills Rating, Undated (Box 41, Folder 3)
      An article about skills wanted in the job market.
    - National California Quality of Life Survey, Undated (Box 41, Folder 4)
      An article about growth in California.
    - National "Downtown" Office Space, January 1990 (Box 41, Folder 5)
      An article about businesses being located in downtown areas.
    - Development Results of DuPage County, September-October 1991 (Box 41, Folder 6)
      Correspondence, a newsletter and "Impacts of Development on DuPage County Property Taxes".
    - The Environment, September 1990 (Box 41, Folder 7)
      An article about the effect of growth on the environment.
    - National Consumer Survey Home Buyers, December 1987-February 1990 (Box 41, Folder 8)
      Correspondence, advertisements, magazines and articles about the housing market.
    - National Immigrants, Undated (Box 41, Folder 9)
      An article about immigration between 1889 and 1987
    - National Canadian Census, February 1988 (Box 41, Folder 10)
      Information about the 1986 Canadian census.
    - National Family Income, November 1988 (Box 41, Folder 11)
      An article about areas with high income and an article about Americans.
    - National Income Per Household, April 1989 (Box 41, Folder 12)
      Articles about household incomes.
    - National Income Per Capita Boston-New England, September 1987 (Box 41, Folder 13)
      Articles about person income.
    - National Growing Urban Areas, March-January 1989 (Box 41, Folder 14)
      A 1990 Real Estate Market Forecast and articles about fast growing urban areas.
    - Highway Fact Book, Undated (Box 41, Folder 15)
      Documents about the nation's highway program.
    - Economic Change of D.C., November 1991 (Box 41, Folder 16)
      Articles about economic and social change in Washington, D.C.
    - Demographic Characteristics of Blacks, 1990 (Box 41, Folder 17)
      "Selected Demographic Characteristics of Blacks in States of the United States".
    - Social, Economic, Political, and Geographical Experience of Blacks, 1990 (Box 41, Folder 18)
      "The Social, Economic, Political, and Geographical Experience of Blacks in Selected Cities".
    - Chronology of Black America, 1990 (Box 41, Folder 19)
      "Chronology: People, Places, Events, and Dates of Importance to the Black Community".
    - The Changing Face of Cities, November 1991 (Box 41, Folder 20)
      Articles about minorities in cities.
    - Income and Ethnic Groups, September 1989-May 1991 (Box 41, Folder 21)
      An article about high incomes and a chapter of a book about ethnic groups in America.
    - Planner's Data Book for Bergen County, 1988 (Box 41, Folder 22)
      "The 1988 Planner's Data Book for Bergen County: Current Municipal and County Data From Census and Non-Census Sources".
    - Chicago Numbers Jobs, May 1990 (Box 41, Folder 23)
      An article about the Chicago, Illinois economy.
    - Delaware Valley, February 1991-April 1992 (Box 41, Folder 24)
      Information tables, correspondence and other information about the 1990 Census in the Delaware Valley Regional Planning Commission.
    - Market Reports, August-September 1988 (Box 41, Folder 25)
      Reports on market opportunity for office and research and development land uses in Massachusetts.
    - Charles Lesser Market Report, September 1988-April 1989 (Box 42, Folder 1)
      Reviews of commercial real estate trends and market opportunities.
    - Local Baltimore General Stats, January 1981 (Box 42, Folder 2)
      "Metropolitan Baltimore in the 1970s: A Decade of Change".
    - Local Aging, May 1989 (Box 42, Folder 3)
      Articles about aging in the Washington, D.C. area.
    - Local Numbers, May 1988-July 1990 (Box 42, Folder 4)
      Articles about the largest public companies in Washington, D.C. and Washington area housing.
    - Local Commercial Construction, March 1989-June 1990 (Box 42, Folder 5)
      Articles about the office market in Virginia and Washington, D.C.
    - Transportation, December 1982 (Box 42, Folder 6)
      The summary of findings of and technical supplement to the Long Range Transportation Plan Re-Evaluation.
    - Transportation, January 1988 (Box 42, Folder 7)
      "Suburban Employment Center Cordon Counts of Vehicular and Passenger Volumes" from the Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments.
    - Transportation, January 1989-January 1990 (Box 42, Folder 8)
      "Transportation Facts and Forecasts for the Washington Metropolitan Region" and "1989 Beltway Cordon Count of Vehicular and Passenger Volumes" from the Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments.
    - Transportation, May 1990 (Box 42, Folder 9)
      The final report of the National Strategic Transportation Planning Study for the Washington Metropolitan Region.
    - Retail Space Construction D.C. Area, September 1988-July 1989 (Box 42, Folder 10)
      Articles about the construction of retail space in Washington, D.C.
    - Local Retail Sales, January 1990 (Box 42, Folder 11)
      An article about Washington D.C. retail sales.
    - Retail Space Prices, December 1988-March 1991 (Box 42, Folder 12)
      Articles about the cost of retail space.
    - Local D.C. Area Statistics, November 1982-May 1989 (Box 43, Folder 1)
      Articles and books about economic growth in Washington, D.C.
    - D.C. Climate, December 1989 (Box 43, Folder 2)
      An article, charts and graphs about the climate of the Washington, D.C. area.
    - Local Population, November 1979-May 19909 (Box 43, Folder 3)
      Graphs and charts of population growth, population estimates and demographic trend documents.
    - Office Space D.C.-VA-MD, December 1988-October 1990 (Box 43, Folder 4)
      Articles about available office space in the Washington, D.C. metropolitan area.
    - Local Office Space: Square Footage, March 1989 (Box 43, Folder 5)
      A list of Washington, D.C. metropolitan area neighborhoods by office space.
    - Local Office Space Federal Government, September 1988-February 1989 (Box 43, Folder 6)
      Articles about Federal Government office construction in the Washington, D.C. area.
    - Supermarket Chain Sales, August 1990 (Box 43, Folder 7)
      An article about a rise in the number of supermarket chains in the Washington, D.C. area.
    - Local New Residents, December 1988-June 1989 (Box 43, Folder 8)
      Articles and graphs about people moving to the Washington, D.C. area.
    - Local Jobs, September 1987-July 1990 (Box 43, Folder 9)
      Articles and newsletters about employment rates in the Washington, D.C. area.
    - Local Income, May 1987-October 1989 (Box 43, Folder 10)
      Notes, articles and newsletters about income rates in the Washington, D.C. area. Also included is information about the Virginia Adjusted Gross Income and a list of holidays.
    - Local Per Capita Income, March 1990-April 1992 (Box 43, Folder 11)
      An article about per capita income in Northern Virginia and a business review from the Federal Reserve Bank of Philadelphia
    - Local Growth and Transportation, November 1989 (Box 43, Folder 12)
      "The 1990's and Beyond: Critical Choices for the Washington Metropolitan Reason" from a regional conference on growth and transportation.
    - Local Market Trends, September 1984-November 1989 (Box 43, Folder 13)
      Newsletters, press releases and research memos about trends in the market.
    - Local Economy, December 1989 (Box 43, Folder 14)